Guide to the Anthony Trollope Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Anthony Trollope collection
1835-1940
1835-1881
GEN MSS 272
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.81
(6 boxes)
The collection consists of six autograph manuscript novels or parts of novels, notes, notebooks, and two letters by Anthony Trollope.
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882 ( Can you forgive her?)
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882 ( Cousin Henry)
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882 ( Dr. Wortle's School)
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882 ( Ayala's angel)
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882 ( Harry Heathcote of Gangoil, Christmas Story for the Graphic)
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882 ( Land Leaguers)
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882 ( Last chronicle of Barset)
Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882 ( Sir Harry Hotspur of Humblethwaite)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials acquired by gift and purchase from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Chauncey Brewster Tinker Manuscript Collection (GEN MSS 310). General Collection, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Existence and Location of Copies
The entire collection, excepting the two letters, is available on microfilm from the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Scope and Contents
The Anthony Trollope Collection consists of six autograph manuscript novels or parts of novels, a commonplace book, and two letters by Anthony Trollope. The collection spans the years 1835-[1940?], but most of the material dates from Trollope's adult life, 1835-1881. The collection is housed in six boxes and is organized into two series: Writings and Other Papers.
Series I, Writings, consists of the novels Can You Forgive Her?, with autograph corrections by Trollope; The Last Chronicle of Barset, with corrections by Trollope; Ayala's Angel, half in the hand of Florence Bland, Trollope's niece, with portions of chapters 39 and 41 and the whole of chapter 40 lacking; Cousin Henry, chapters 1-24, half in the hand of Florence Bland; Dr. Wortle's School, half of it dictated to Mrs. Trollope or to Florence Bland; Harry Heathcote of Gangoil, Christmas Story for the Graphic; and Sir Harry Hotspur of Humblethwaite. There is also a manuscript outline and notes, in Trollope's handwriting, for his unfinished novel, The Landleaguers.
Series II, Other Papers, consists of a two volume commonplace book containing notes on books he has read, each volume carrying his signature and the date, August 1835. Also in the series is a letter to C. Collins, dated 1879 Apr 14, and a photostat copy of a letter to G. C. Cornwall about the practicability of extending free postal delivery in rural areas, dated 1857 Apr 18.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Commonplace books; Bland, Florence; Trollope, Anthony, 1815-1882
- Writings, 1864-1881; Series I; 1.4; (3.5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Writings, consists of eight autograph manuscript novels.
  - AYALA'S ANGEL
    - Chapters 1-7, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1881] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chapters 8-15, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1881] (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Chapters 16-24, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1881] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chapters 25-32, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1881] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Chapters 33-46, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1881] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Chapters 47-56, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1881] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Chapters 57-64, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1881] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CAN YOU FORGIVE HER?
    - Chapters 1-4, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Chapters 5-9, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Chapters 10-15, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Chapters 16-22, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Chapters 23-29, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Chapters 30-35, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Chapters 36-40, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Chapters 41-47, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Chapters 48-55, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Chapters 56-60, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Chapters 61-65, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Chapters 66-71, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Chapters 72-76, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Chapters 77-80, autograph manuscript, 1864-65 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - COUSIN HENRY
    - Chapters 1-9, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1879] (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Chapters 10-18, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1879] (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Chapters 19-24, autograph manuscript, [ca. 1879] (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - DR. WORTLE'S SCHOOL
    - Chapters 1-7, autograph manuscript, [1879] (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Chapters 8-14, autograph manuscript, [1879] (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Chapters 15-24, autograph manuscript, [1879] (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - HARRY HEATHCOTE OF GANGOIL
    - Chapters 1-3, autograph manuscript, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Chapters 4-8, autograph manuscript, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Chapters 9-12, autograph manuscript, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - THE LANDLEAGUERS
    - Autograph manuscript outline and notes (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - THE LAST CHRONICLE OF BARSET
    - Chapters 1-3, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Chapters 4-8, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Chapters 9-14, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Chapters 15-19, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Chapters 20-24, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Chapters 25-31, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Chapters 32-35, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Chapters 36-41, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Chapters 42-46, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Chapters 47-50, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Chapters 51-55, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Chapters 56-59, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Chapters 60-63, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Chapters 64-69, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Chapters 70-75, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Chapters 76-81, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Chapters 82-84, autograph manuscript, 1866-67 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - SIR HARRY HOTSPUR OF HUMBLETHWAITE
    - Chapters 1-8, autograph manuscript, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Chapters 9-14, autograph manuscript, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Chapters 15-20, autograph manuscript, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Chapters 21-24, autograph manuscript, 1870 (Box 4, Folder 52)
- Other Papers, 1835-1940; Series II; 0.41; (2.5 boxes)
  Series II, Other Papers, consists of a commonplace book and letters.
  - Trollope, Anthony. Photostat copy of an ALS to G. C. Cornwall dated 1857 Apr 18, [Tuin?], [1940?] (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Trollope, Anthony. ALS to C. Collins, London, 1879 Apr 14 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Commonplace book with notes on books he has read [volume 1 of 2], [ca. 1835] (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Commonplace book with notes on books he has read [volume 2 of 2], [ca. 1835] (Box 6, Folder 56)